So there's a lot of valid concern these days
ينصب اهتمامنا الواضح هذه الأيام
that our technology is getting so smart
على تطور ذكاء التكنولوجيا الملحوظ
that we've put ourselves on the path to a jobless future.
وأننا قد أوقعنا بأنفسنا في فخ البطالة في المستقبل
And I think the example of a self-driving car
وأعتقد أن السيارة ذات القيادة الذاتية
is actually the easiest one to see.
هي بالفعل خير دليل يمكننا أن نلحظه.
So these are going to be fantastic for all kinds of different reasons.
ولذلك سيظل هذا المثال واقعيًا حتى إن تعددت الأسباب واختلفت.
But did you know that "driver" is actually the most common job
ولكن هل تعلم أن "القيادة" تعد أكثر المهن انتشارًا
in 29 of the 50 US states?
في 29 ولاية أمريكية من أصل 50 ولاية؟
What's going to happen to these jobs when we're no longer driving our cars
ما هو مستقبل هذه المهن إذا توقفنا عن قيادة سياراتنا
or cooking our food
أو طهي طعامنا
or even diagnosing our own diseases?
أو حتى تشخيص أمراضنا الصحية؟
Well, a recent study from Forrester Research
حسنًا، إن دراسة حديثة من أبحاث (فوريستر)
goes so far to predict that 25 million jobs
قد تنبأت بأن 25 مليون وظيفة
might disappear over the next 10 years.
يحتمل انقراضهم في غضون 10 سنوات القادمة.
To put that in perspective,
ولكي نكون أكثر موضوعية
that's three times as many jobs lost in the aftermath of the financial crisis.
إن هذا الرقم هو ثلاثة أضعاف الوظائف التي انتهى زمنها عقب الأزمة المالية العالمية.
And it's not just blue-collar jobs that are at risk.
وبالتأكيد لن يكون يقتصر الخطر على العمال والحرفيين.
On Wall Street and across Silicon Valley, we are seeing tremendous gains
فى "وول ستريت" و عبر "وادي السيليكون"، اننا نشهد مكاسب هائلة
in the quality of analysis and decision-making
في نوعية التحليل وصنع القرار
because of machine learning.
بسبب تعلّم الآلة.
So even the smartest, highest-paid people will be affected by this change.
ولذا فإنه حتى الأذكياء أصحاب الرواتب المرتفعة سيتأثرون بهذا التغير .
What's clear is that no matter what your job is,
إن الأمر الواضح أمامنا أنه مهما تكن مهنتك
at least some, if not all of your work,
فإنه على الأقل، إن لم يكن جميع عملك،
is going to be done by a robot or software in the next few years.
سيقوم بأدائه إنسان آلي أو برنامجًا حاسوبيًا في السنوات القليلة المقبلة.
And that's exactly why people like Mark Zuckerberg and Bill Gates
ولهذا السبب هناك أناس مثل: (مارك زوكربيرج) و(بيل جيتس)
are talking about the need for government-funded minimum income levels.
يتحدثون عن احتياج أصحاب الدخل المنخفض إلى تمويل من الحكومة.
But if our politicians can't agree on things like health care
ولكن إذا لم يستطع الساسة الإتفاق على أشياء مثل الرعاية الصحية
or even school lunches,
أو وجبات الغداء المدرسي،
I just don't see a path where they'll find consensus
فأنا لا أرى أرضًا مشتركة يمكنهم الإتفاق
on something as big and as expensive as universal basic life income.
فيها على شيء كبير وهام مثل أساسيات الدخل الحيوية.
Instead, I think the response needs to be led by us in industry.
وبالمقابل، أعتقد أنه لابد أن تصدرالإستجابة منَّا نحن في عالم الصناعة.
We have to recognize the change that's ahead of us
لابد أن ندرك التغيير الذي يطرأ علينا
and start to design the new kinds of jobs
ونبدأ في تصميم وإيجاد وظائف جديدة
that will still be relevant in the age of robotics.
يمكن أن تثبت نفعيتها في عصر الروبوتات.
The good news is that we have faced down and recovered
إن الأخبار الجيدة أننا قد واجهنا مثل هذه الإنتكاسة
two mass extinctions of jobs before.
ونهضنا من عمليتي انقراض للوظائف من قبل.
From 1870 to 1970,
في الفترة بين 1870 إلى 1970،
the percent of American workers based on farms fell by 90 percent,
انخفض معدل المزارعون الأمريكيون الذين يعتمدون على الزراعة بنسبة 90 بالمئة،
and then again from 1950 to 2010,
وأيضًا منذ عام 1950 إلى عام 2010،
the percent of Americans working in factories
انخفض معدل العمال الأمريكيون في المصانع
fell by 75 percent.
بنسبة 75 بالمئة.
The challenge we face this time, however, is one of time.
إن التحدي الذي نواجهه هذه المرة، هو الوقت.
We had a hundred years to move from farms to factories,
لقد استغرقنا مائة عام للإنتقال من الزراعة إلى الصناعة،
and then 60 years to fully build out a service economy.
و60 عامًا أخرى لبناء وتسهيل خدمات اقتصادية.
The rate of change today
إن معدل التغيير اليوم
suggests that we may only have 10 or 15 years to adjust,
يخبرنا أننا ربما نمتلك من 10 إلى 15 عامًا فقط للتأقلم،
and if we don't react fast enough,
وإذا لم نتخذ ردة فعل سريعة
that means by the time today's elementary-school students
فإنه بمرور الوقت سيصبح طلاب المدارس الإبتدائية
are college-aged,
في عمر الجامعة
we could be living in a world that's robotic,
وسنعيش في عالم من الروبوتات
largely unemployed and stuck in kind of un-great depression.
تجتاحه البطالة، ويغطيه حالة من الإكتئاب.
But I don't think it has to be this way.
ولكن لا أعتقد أن الأمر سيسير بهذا الشكل.
You see, I work in innovation,
كما ترون، أنا أعمل في الإبتكار
and part of my job is to shape how large companies apply new technologies.
وجزءًا من عملي هو تحديد كيف يمكن للشركات الكبيرة تطبيقات التكنولوجيا الحديثة.
Certainly some of these technologies
بالتأكيد بعض هذه التقنيات
are even specifically designed to replace human workers.
مصممة خصيصاً لتحل محل العمال البشريين.
But I believe that if we start taking steps right now
ولكن أعتقد أنه إذا بدأنا في اتخاذ الخطوات من الآن
to change the nature of work,
لتغيير طبيعة العمل،
we can not only create environments where people love coming to work
لا يمكننا فقط خلق بيئات حيث يحب الناس القدوم للعمل
but also generate the innovation that we need
ولكن أيضا توليد الابتكار الذي نحتاج إليه
to replace the millions of jobs that will be lost to technology.
لتحل محل الملايين من الوظائف التي ستذهب للتكنولوجيا.
I believe that the key to preventing our jobless future
وأعتقد أن المفتاح لمنع مستقبلنا من البطالة
is to rediscover what makes us human,
هو إعادة اكتشاف ما يجعلنا الإنسان،
and to create a new generation of human-centered jobs
وخلق جيل جديد من الوظائف التي تتمحور حول الإنسان
that allow us to unlock the hidden talents and passions
التي تسمح لنا لاكتشاف المواهب و الشغف
that we carry with us every day.
الذى نحمله معنا كل يوم.
But first, I think it's important to recognize
ولكن أولاً، أعتقد من المهم الاعتراف
that we brought this problem on ourselves.
أننا جلبنا هذه المشكلة لأنفسنا.
And it's not just because, you know, we are the one building the robots.
وهذا ليس فقط لأنه، كما تعلمون، نحن نصنع الروبوتات.
But even though most jobs left the factory decades ago,
ولكن على الرغم من أن معظم الوظائف تركت المصنع منذ عقود،
we still hold on to this factory mindset
ونحن ما زلنا متمسكين بعقلية المصنع
of standardization and de-skilling.
من التقييس وإزالة المهارة.
We still define jobs around procedural tasks
ما زلنا نحدد الوظائف على حسب المهام الإجرائية
and then pay people for the number of hours that they perform these tasks.
ومن ثم ندفع الناس على حسب عدد من الساعات التي يؤدون فيها هذه المهام.
We've created narrow job definitions
لقد وضعنا مفهومات ضيقة للوظائف
like cashier, loan processor or taxi driver
مثل أمين الصندوق، ومعالج القرض أو سائق سيارة أجرة
and then asked people to form entire careers
ثم طلبنا من الناس تشكيل مهن كاملة
around these singular tasks.
على تلك المهام الصغيرة
These choices have left us with actually two dangerous side effects.
وقد تركت لنا هذه الخيارات اثنين من الآثار الجانبية الخطيرة.
The first is that these narrowly defined jobs
الأول هو أن هذه الوظائف المحددة بدقة
will be the first to be displaced by robots,
ستكون أول الوظائف التى ستستبدل من قبل الروبوتات
because single-task robots are just the easiest kinds to build.
لأن الروبوتات ذات المهمة الواحدة سهلة البناء.
But second, we have accidentally made it
ولكن ثانيا، لقد جعلنا عن طريق الخطأ
so that millions of workers around the world
بحيث الملايين من العمال حول العالم
have unbelievably boring working lives.
لديهم حياة عمل مملة بشكل لا يصدق.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Let's take the example of a call center agent.
لنأخذ المثال من وكيل مركز الاتصال.
Over the last few decades, we brag about lower operating costs
في العقود القليلة الأخيرة، نحن نتباهي بتكاليف التشغيل المنخفضة
because we've taken most of the need for brainpower
لأننا أخذنا معظم ما نحتاجه من القوة العقلية
out of the person and put it into the system.
خارجة من الشخص و وضعها في النظام.
For most of their day, they click on screens,
في معظم أوقاتهم، ينقرون على الشاشات،
they read scripts.
يقرأون النصوص.
They act more like machines than humans.
يتصرفون مثل الآلات أكثر من البشر.
And unfortunately, over the next few years,
ولسوء الحظ، على مدى السنوات القليلة المقبلة،
as our technology gets more advanced,
كما أصبحت التكنولوجيا لدينا أكثر تقدماً،
they, along with people like clerks and bookkeepers,
هم، جنباً إلى جنب مع الناس مثل الكتبة وكتاب الحسابات،
will see the vast majority of their work disappear.
سوف يروا الغالبية العظمى من عملهم تختفي.
To counteract this, we have to start creating new jobs
لمواجهة هذا، علينا أن نبدأ في خلق وظائف جديدة
that are less centered on the tasks that a person does
أقل تركيزًا على المهام التي يقوم بها الشخص
and more focused on the skills that a person brings to work.
وأكثر تركيزا على المهارات التى يجلبها الشخص للعمل.
For example, robots are great at repetitive and constrained work,
على سبيل المثال، الروبوتات رائعة في العمل المتكرر والمقيّد،
but human beings have an amazing ability
لكن البشر لديهم قدرة مذهلة
to bring together capability with creativity
لتقديم القدرة مع الإبداع
when faced with problems that we've never seen before.
عند مواجهة مشاكل لم يروها من قبل.
It's when every day brings a little bit of a surprise
عندما يجلب كل يوم قليلاً من المفاجأة
that we have designed work for humans
أننا قمنا بتصميم عمل للبشر
and not for robots.
و ليس للروبوتات.
Our entrepreneurs and engineers already live in this world,
ان رواد الأعمال والمهندسين يعيشون بالفعل في هذا العالم،
but so do our nurses and our plumbers
ولكن كذلك الممرضات والسباكين
and our therapists.
والمعالجين.
You know, it's the nature of too many companies and organizations
كما تعلمون، إنها طبيعة العديد من الشركات والمنظمات
to just ask people to come to work and do your job.
لتطلب فقط من الناس أن يأتوا إلى العمل و يقوموا به.
But if you work is better done by a robot,
ولكن إذا كان عملك يُنجَز أفضل بواسطة روبوت،
or your decisions better made by an AI,
أو قراراتك تُتخَذ على نحو أفضل من قبل الذكاء الاصطناعى،
what are you supposed to be doing?
ماذا يفترض بك أن تفعل؟
Well, I think for the manager,
حسنا، أعتقد كمدير،
we need to realistically think about the tasks that will be disappearing
نحن بحاجة للتفكير بواقعية في المهام التي سوف تختفي على مدى
over the next few years
السنوات القليلة المقبلة
and start planning for more meaningful, more valuable work that should replace it.
و بدء التخطيط لاستبدالهم بوظائف ذات عمل و قيمة.
We need to create environments
نحن بحاجة لإنشاء بيئات
where both human beings and robots thrive.
حيث تزدهر كل من البشر والروبوتات.
I say, let's give more work to the robots,
أقول، دعونا نعطي المزيد من العمل إلى الروبوتات،
and let's start with the work that we absolutely hate doing.
ودعنا نبدأ بالعمل الذي نكره تمامًا.
Here, robot,
هنا، روبوت،
process this painfully idiotic report.
عالج هذا التقرير الغبي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And move this box. Thank you.
و حرك هذا الصندوق. شكراً.
And for the human beings,
و بالنسبة للبشر،
we should follow the advice from Harry Davis at the University of Chicago.
يجب علينا اتباع نصيحة (هاري ديفيس) في جامعة "شيكاغو".
He says we have to make it so that people don't leave too much of themselves
يقول علينا أن نفعلها حتى لا يترك الناس الكثير من أنفسهم
in the trunk of their car.
في صندوق سيارتهم.
I mean, human beings are amazing on weekends.
أعني، البشر مدهشون في عطلة نهاية الأسبوع.
Think about the people that you know and what they do on Saturdays.
فكر في الأشخاص الذين تعرفهم وماذا يفعلون يوم السبت.
They're artists, carpenters, chefs and athletes.
انهم فنانين ونجارين، طهاة ورياضيين.
But on Monday, they're back to being Junior HR Specialist
لكن يوم الاثنين، يعودوا لكونهم أخصائيين الموارد البشرية
and Systems Analyst 3.
و محلل نظم 3.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You know, these narrow job titles not only sound boring,
أنت تعرف، هذه الألقاب الصغيرة ليس فقط مملة،
but they're actually a subtle encouragement
لكنهم في الواقع وسائل تشجيع خفية
for people to make narrow and boring job contributions.
للناس ليجعلوا مساهمات العمل ضيقة و مملة.
But I've seen firsthand that when you invite people to be more,
لكنني رأيت مباشرة أنه عندما تدعو الناس ليكونوا أكثر ابداعاً،
they can amaze us with how much more they can be.
يمكنهم أن يدهشونا بكم الابداع الذى يمكن الوصول له.
A few years ago, I was working at a large bank
منذ عدة سنوات، كنت أعمل في بنك كبير
that was trying to bring more innovation into its company culture.
التي كانت تحاول جلب المزيد من الابتكار في ثقافة الشركة.
So my team and I designed a prototyping contest
لذا صممت أنا وفريقي مسابقة نماذج
that invited anyone to build anything that they wanted.
التي تدعو أي شخص لبناء أي شيء يريدونه.
We were actually trying to figure out
كنا في الواقع نحاول معرفة
whether or not the primary limiter to innovation
سواء كان المحدد الأساسي للابتكار
was a lack of ideas or a lack of talent,
هو الافتقار إلى الأفكار أم الافتقار إلى الموهبة،
and it turns out it was neither one.
واتضح أنه لم يكن واحد منهم.
It was an empowerment problem.
كانت مشكلة تمكين.
And the results of the program were amazing.
و نتائج البرنامج كانت مذهلة.
We started by inviting people to reenvision
بدأنا بدعوة الناس لتصور
what it is they could bring to a team.
ما يستطيعون أن يقدمونه للمجموعة.
This contest was not only a chance to build anything that you wanted
هذه المسابقة ليست مجرد فرصة لبناء أي شيء تريده
but also be anything that you wanted.
ولكن أيضاً أي شيء تريده.
And when people were no longer limited by their day-to-day job titles,
وعندما لم يعد الناس مُقًيدين بألقابهم الوظيفية اليومية،
they felt free to bring all kinds of different skills and talents
شعروا بالحرية لجلب جميع أنواع المهارات والمواهب المختلفة
to the problems that they were trying to solve.
للمشاكل التي كانوا يحاولون حلها.
We saw technology people being designers, marketing people being architects,
رأينا التكنولوجيين أصبحوا المصممين، المسوقين أصبحوا مهندسين معماريين،
and even finance people showing off their ability to write jokes.
وحتى الاقتصاديين أظهروا قدرتهم على كتابة النكات.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We ran this program twice,
فعلنا هذا البرنامج مرتين،
and each time more than 400 people brought their unexpected talents to work
وفي كل مرة أكثر من 400 شخص جلبت مواهبهم الغير متوقعة للعمل
and solved problems that they had been wanting to solve for years.
وحلوا المشاكل التي كانوا يرغبوا في حلها لسنوات.
Collectively, they created millions of dollars of value,
جماعياً، خلقوا ملايين الدولارات،
building things like a better touch-tone system for call centers,
من خلال بناء أشياء مثل نظام نغمات باللمس أفضل لمراكز الاتصال،
easier desktop tools for branches
أدوات سطح المكتب أسهل للفروع
and even a thank you card system
وحتى نظام "شكراً لك" في البطاقة
that has become a cornerstone of the employee working experience.
التي أصبحت حجر أساسى للموظف في خبرة العمل.
Over the course of the eight weeks,
على مدار الأسابيع الثمانية،
people flexed muscles that they never dreamed of using at work.
استخدم الناس مهارات لم يحلموا باستخدامها في العمل.
People learned new skills,
تعلم الناس مهارات جديدة،
they met new people,
التقوا بأشخاص جدد،
and at the end, somebody pulled me aside and said,
وفي النهاية ، شخص ما سحبني جانباً وقال:
"I have to tell you,
"يجب ان اخبرك،
the last few weeks has been one of the most intense,
كانت الأسابيع القليلة الماضية واحدة من أكثر الأسابيع،
hardest working experiences of my entire life,
من أشد، و أصعب خبرة عمل في كل حياتي،
but not one second of it felt like work."
ولكن ولا ثانية شعرت بالعمل ".
And that's the key.
وهذه هي الفكرة.
For those few weeks, people got to be creators and innovators.
في تلك الأسابيع القليلة ، الناس كانوا مبدعين ومبتكرين.
They had been dreaming of solutions
كانوا يحلمون بحل
to problems that had been bugging them for years,
للمشاكل التي كانت تزعجهم لسنوات،
and this was a chance to turn those dreams into a reality.
وكانت هذه فرصة لتحويل تلك الأحلام إلى واقع.
And that dreaming is an important part of what separates us from machines.
وهذا الحلم جزء مهم فيما يفصلنا عن الآلات.
For now, our machines do not get frustrated,
في الوقت الراهن، لدينا آلات لا تشعر بالإحباط،
they do not get annoyed,
لا ينزعجون،
and they certainly don't imagine.
وبالتأكيد لا يتخيلون.
But we, as human beings --
لكننا كبشر --
we feel pain,
نشعر بالألم،
we get frustrated.
نشعر بالإحباط.
And it's when we're most annoyed and most curious
وعندما يملأنا الغضب والفضول
that we're motivated to dig into a problem and create change.
نكون متحفزين ومتحمسين للبحث عن المشكلة واحداث الفارق.
Our imaginations are the birthplace of new products, new services,
خيالنا هو مهد المنتجات الجديدة والخدمات الجديدة
and even new industries.
وحتى الصناعات الجديدة.
I believe that the jobs of the future
أعتقد أن وظائف المستقبل
will come from the minds of people
ستأتي من عقول الناس
who today we call analysts and specialists,
الذين نسميهم اليوم المحللين والمتخصصين،
but only if we give them the freedom and protection that they need to grow
ولكن فقط إذا منحناهم الحرية والحماية التي يحتاجونها ليصبحوا
into becoming explorers and inventors.
مستكشفين و مخترعين.
If we really want to robot-proof our jobs,
إذا أردنا حقًا أن نحمي وظائفنا من الروبوت،
we, as leaders, need to get out of the mindset
نحن، كقادة، بحاجة للخروج من عقلية
of telling people what to do
إخبار الناس ماذا يفعلون
and instead start asking them what problems they're inspired to solve
وبدلاً من ذلك أسألهم عن المشاكل التي ألهمتهم لحلها
and what talents they want to bring to work.
وما هي المواهب التى يريدون أن تأتي إلى العمل.
Because when you can bring your Saturday self to work on Wednesdays,
لأنه عندما يمكنك إحضار يوم السبت الخاص بك للعمل يوم الأربعاء،
you'll look forward to Mondays more,
سوف نتطلع إلى أيام الاثنين أكثر،
and those feelings that we have about Mondays
وهذه المشاعر التي لدينا حول أيام الاثنين
are part of what makes us human.
هي جزء مما يجعلنا بشراً.
And as we redesign work for an era of intelligent machines,
و بينما نحن نقوم بإعادة تصميم العمل لتمهيد عصر من الآلات الذكية،
I invite you all to work alongside me
أدعوكم جميعًا للعمل بجانبي
to bring more humanity to our working lives.
لجلب المزيد من الإنسانية لحياتنا العاملة.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)